U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs 5003 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series XXXI: Terminal Railroad Association of St. Louis: St. Louis Union Station and surrounding yards
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Towards West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    Tracks curving to the left, signals in ground. Also overhead obstruction (bridge), crossover controlled by Tower operator. Tracks used for incoming trains and also to cut off passing cars to be switched onto other trains. Cars at left of photo are being switched by Missouri Pacific RR. Note tracks at top left of photo converging from both directions. (like p-17/18)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Towards West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    Tracks curving to the left, signals in ground. Also overhead obstruction (bridge), crossover controlled by Tower operator. Tracks used for incoming trains and also to cut off passing cars to be switched onto other trains. Cars at left of photo are being switched by Missouri Pacific RR. Note tracks at top left of photo converging from both directions. (like P-17/18)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge to the West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 7)
    This view is to the west from the 18th Street bridge. The freight yard is at the right of the photograph. Note the engine on the extreme end of freight train (center of photo). The fireman has the curve on his side and only he can see in front and to the rear of the locomotive the ground personnel and other movements to his left. Cars being switched in this yard come from the left center of the picture. There are other train movements at the upper right of the picture. Firemen can and do observe passenger trains departing and entering Union Station and also their own trains for defects.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Photo from 18th Street Bridge St. Louis to the West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    Train in center of photo moving with engineer out of view, if necessary to jam signals any mishap on train would be impossible for him to operate. Fireman in good position to see ahead and also to rear. Cars moving to the left of same fireman and man on ground between trains. Trains at right of photo being shoved to station; again fireman observing effect of course of rail etc.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Looking West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 22)
    This view is to the west from the 18th Street bridge. The building in upper center of photograph is the operational tower which controls the bridge and ground signals in and around Union Station. Workmen in lower half of photograph are dangerously close to tracks with no form of protection. Notice the debris and rubbish between the tracks. Tracks to right and left. Crossover from one lead to another. Train men working on ground in lower part of photo very close to rail, on left side of one track, could be hit if not observed by fireman. Signals on ground and also overhead bridges to right of photo.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 22)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Looking West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 23)
    Same as P-11, except train of freight cars is at upper left of photo. Again note men working at bottom of photo. This is another view to the west from the 18th Street Bridge. This shows more clearly how all the tracks at left of photograph curve to the left.Note also the workmen in the lower part of the picture as for whom no protection is provided against trains pulling into the freight yards at the left. The fireman is their only real protection since he has the best view on the curves. Notice also the movement of the train at the upper right of the photograph and of the ground signals and water hydrants at left center of picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 23)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Looking West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 25)
    Note signals on overhead bridge; hard to determine at different times of day due to position of sun. Again, tracks converging from under bridge to under bridge #5; ground signals as well as overhead signals used to make movement here. Debris in and around tracks. Building in center of photograph is the operational tower which controls the bridge and ground control signals This view is similar to P-11 but note the ground signal at lower right center of photograph and the signal bridge at upper center of picture. When yard engines shove or when road engines back into the station the fireman has the view of the bridge signals and ground signals.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 25)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Looking East, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 26)
    Showing part of mail and express yards at left of photo. Freight yards at right. Note position of passenger train and converging tracks on fireman's side of passenger train; also workmen in lower left of photo. Notice cab of Diesel locomotive at extreme left, fireman in excellent position to observe any irregularities on moving passenger train, workmen in lower part of photo. Unkempt yard conditions. This view to the east from the 18th Street Bridge is similar to photograph P-4 and shows some workmen and trains in different positions. The train in the center is being shoved into the station. Notice the cab of the engine at the extreme left of the photograph which indicates how close the movements are. The cars at the extreme right are in the freight yard and show the proximity of freight and passenger movements. The engine at the extreme left center shows that the fireman has the view of adjacent tracks in back-up movements.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 26)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge Looking East, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 27)
    Notice position of engine in left of photo. Fireman has converging tracks, with cars on them also trains on lead to protect, as engineer is watching his side, also converging tracks. Engine in center of photo, has a threefold job. Trains on each side and workmen in front of diesel (foreground) unkempt yard condition. The easterly view from the 18th Street Bridge shows movement of trains and engines, workmen in the center of photograph, congestion of tracks, close clearances and conditions of the yard. The fireman on the engine in the upper center of the photograph behind the passenger train has an excellent view of the passenger train to observe any irregularities as it passes. The cars on the track at the left of the photograph are used to load mail and express, and the close clearance and fouling points there are best observed by the fireman on the engine at the left center of the photograph.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 27)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 27)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge to the Northwest, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 28a)
    Notice curvature of tracks leading into Union Station. Signals on overhead bridge (#10). Very hard to distinguish in morning due to sun shining on them. Also no vision around building, also tracks merging together beyond N Bridge #10. Again debris around and between tracks. Weed in upper left of photo. Also note conditions of stub tracks in center of photo. This view to the northwest from the 18th Street Bridge shows curvature and converging of tracks, bridge signals, and stub tracks at center of photograph. The view of the signal bridge is obstructed by the building. Notice also rubbish and trash in and on the tracks.
  - View from 18th Street Bridge to the Northwest, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 28b)
    Closeness of trains in center of photo under overhead bridge #6. Again, tracks coming together at this point. Fireman on Diesel (partly showing) has excellent view of separating passenger train, and can notice any irregularities of same. Man walking dangerously close to outside rail on curve. Debris between tracks. Passenger train GM&O No. 100, Unit: E7A locomotive. This view is similar to P-23 and P-24 but shows the further movement of the trains. Note how the fireman on the yard engine can see the movement of the outbound GM&O train and also ahead on the curvature of the tracks. The fireman on the road engine can look back and check his train but the engineer can only see ahead on such a curve.
    - Item 0: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 28b)
  - View from 18th Street Bridge to the Northwest, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 29)
    Same as P-23 and P-25 with exception of trains moving at extreme left of photo. Note workmen in lower left of photo. This view is similar to P-23 except there is a movement of trains under the bridge signal. Notice the clearance between the two engines in center of photograph. There the fireman can observe the outgoing GM&O train and also ahead in the direction his engine is moving. Note also the workman to the left of the center.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 29)
  - View to the North in 21st Street Passenger Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 30)
    Spotlights at extreme end of yard makes vision limited at night. Extremely dangerous for ground personnel. Debris in foreground of photo. Most work performed on left side of engine in this yard due to curvature of track.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 30)
  - View from Jefferson Avenue Bridge looking West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 31)
    Unlighted walkway directly in front of engine. Used by workmen, (ice men, car cleaners, electricians, etc.) it is protected by the fireman on the left side, while engineer protects right side. Very poor illumination in this yard. Again, curvature and converging tracks limited fireman's view only while coupling the car. Locomotive No. 504
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 31)
  - View from Compton Ave Bridge Looking West, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 32)
    Rankin Avenue coach yard. Not shown in photo: last lights on Compton Ave Bridge; very bright, limiting vision. Also note close clearance of cars and engine in center of photo. Also, obstructed walkway in this yard used by workmen makes it a hazardous operation.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 32)
  - View to the Northeast in 21st Street Passenger Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 34)
    Union Station at left of photo; curvature of tracks to left. Poor lighting limits vision of both engineer and fireman. Signals on ground visible to fireman only while slowing into station.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 34)
  - View to the West in 21st Street Passenger Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 36)
    Yard not lighted. Note oily and unkempt condition of yard. Hand signals passed in this yard exclusively on fireman's side of engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 36)
  - View to East from 21st Street Bridge, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 37)
    Showing ground and overhead bridge signals. Again curvature of tracks to left, right and straight ahead. Converging tracks cross overs, etc. Poor lighting for ground personnel and workmen.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 37)
  - View to East from Scott Avenue, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 38)
    Note Union Station at upper left of photo. Again curvature of tracks to left (fireman's side) dirty and unkempt yard condition; debris alongside track (lower right), ground signals (amber & red only), vision limited due to some floodlights and other improper illumination.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 38)
  - View to West from Compton Avenue Bridge, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 39)
    Note close clearance of cars water hydrants lower left of photo between trains. Poor lighting in this yard. Unkempt, dirty, oily, debris in and around all tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 39)
  - View is to the East from Ewing Avenue, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 40)
    Debris and unkempt condition of tracks. Converging tracks under bridge in upper center of photo. Tracks to left and right there. Ground signals (Red & amber only)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 40)
  - View to the East from East End of Rankin Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 41)
    All tracks curve into the lead. All on left side. Main line on right side of photo (Inbound & outbound). Weeds covering tracks on lower left of photo. Hand signal only in this section of yard. Foot paths used by workmen, dark and very hazardous.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 41)
  - View to the East from Lower East End of Rankin Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 42)
    Outbound and inbound line in extreme right. Engine and car moving into lead must be observed by engine man working on lead in center of photo (foreground). High weed covering tracks also unlighted foot path. All hand signals prevail here.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 42)
  - View to Southeast from East End of Rankin Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 43)
    Showing curvature of rails to left. Note movements of two trains on same lead. Workmen using footpath must be patrolled by engine crews. Note passenger car obstructing half of foot path in upper left of photo. Weeds in upper left, covering tracks. High voltage wires overhead. Very close to train in center of photo. This view is to the east from Compton Avenue Bridge and shows a part of Rankin yard. This is called East Rankin, and is where the Missouri Pacific and the Pennsylvania trains are made up and switched out. The movements of two engines at the upper center, the closeness of the cars on the left of the picture and the ground personnel walking on the footpath give some idea of the dangers always present here. Again, all tracks curve to the left when you leave the yard and to the right when entering the yard. The fireman has to observe the switches and other movements in the back-up move as the engineer receives the signals on his side. The fireman also has to be on the alert for trains coming from the east as one is doing in this picture.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 43)
  - View in West End of Rankin Yard, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 44)
    Tracks converging to left, over grown with weeds in left of photo and all along lead. Engine pulling train in yard to the switch lead. Note position of switch man preparing to pass signals on left side of engine. Also standing on roadway used by supply trucks to deliver supplies to workmen. Other tracks at right of photo for spotting cars for loading or very close clearance. Note building in right center causing view to be obstructed. Note in center at left of photo blocking view of engine men when switching on track in left of photo. Very often the fireman has to locate switchman before shoving cars back on their track. This is a view facing east, and showing again what is called West Rankin yard (see P-21). All signals passed in this part of the yard are on the fireman's side. Notice the left-hand curvature of the tracks, the weeds, and the unkempt condition of this yard. The structure on the upper right is used to supply dining cars and there is very close clearance here. Also, note how visibility is obstructed to the left around the curve and the congestion of track near the center of the photo.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 44)
  - View to the Southwest from 17th Street, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 45)
    Showing express yards. Note close clearance of cars. Obstruction on platforms limiting vision. Weeds covering tracks in center of photo. Debris all over this yard in and on and around tracks. This is a very congested yard and sometimes has as many as seven to ten engines working this yard. This is a push, pulled and spotting of cars for express and mail. This view is to the west from 16th Street. This is referred to as the 17th Street yard, or the mail, baggage, and express yards. There is very close clearance in this yard and all switches are called blind switches due to the fact that they have no lights. One of the blind switches is in the lower left center. The firemen must help observe the line-up on these switches. Upper center of photograph shows a workman walking around the end of a car. Personnel in and about this yard, and express on ramps (right center of photo) are a constant danger that must be observed by the engine crew in this yard to prevent many serious injuries. Tracks curve to the left and right here and at times either the engineer or the fireman alone will have the view.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 45)
  - View to North from 17th Street, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 46)
    Showing, in part, the mail house and express house. Obstruction by building at right. Debris in yard; weeds on tracks. Close clearance between cars and platforms. Curvature of rails all to right, but converging tracks run from left into all leads.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 46)
  - View to the Northeast from 21st Street Bridge, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 47)
    Showing congested movements of trains in and out of Union Station. Note curvature of tracks, ground signals, overhead signals and hand signals prevail here. Note positions of engines as to who can best observe signals. Engines moving in and out of this yard and at times is heavily congested and takes two pairs of eyes to observe conditions to front and rear of engines. This view is also to the east from atop the 21st Street viaduct. Notice the movements of trains and engines in the center of the photograph and the road engine in the lower right. With respect to the engine and cars on the left side of the photograph, hand signals are passed on the fireman's side. Also notice the movements of trains under the bridge signal in the center of the photograph. Close clearances and sharp curves in this plant along with crossovers, ground signals and bridge signals require a lookout by both enginemen.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 47)
  - View to the North from 21st Street Bridge, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 48)
    Showing curvature of tracks all to left side of engine (fireman's). Notice switchman passing signal on fireman's side of engine while engineer is on the alert for any movements from the tracks on his side of engine (right side of photo). Debris, weeds and objects near on and about tracks (left side of photo); also obstruction by building at upper left. Workmen engaged on tracks in upper left. People using walkway in upper center of photo can be best observed by fireman on diesel engine. Also high tension wires across yard overhead. Note the second lead car from engine very low hanging wire over car. This view is to the north from the 21st Street Bridge. It shows that when trains are switched in this yard (21st Street yard) all tracks curve to the fireman's side of the engine. The fireman also has the view of the footpath in the left-center of the photograph which is used by ground personnel. Also notice that the view of the tracks is obstructed by the building at the upper left.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 48)
  - View to the North from 21st Street Bridge, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 49)
    Photo similar to B53F48. Note switchman walking from left side of train. Tracks curving away from engineer. Also note man walking in upper right of photo not operating personnel. Buildings in upper left corner obstructed view and fireman required to take hand signals. Tracks converged at road crossing frequently used by personnel repairing or supplying trains. Note footpath, see photo B53F56 This view is to the north from the 21st Street Bridge. It shows that when trains are switched in this yard (21st Street yard) all tracks curve to the fireman's side of the engine. The fireman also has the view of the footpath in the left-center of the photograph which is used by ground personnel. Also notice that the view of the tracks is obstructed by the building at the upper left.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 49)
  - View to the South, from Inside Union Station, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 50)
    Showing tracks #31 and #32 and movement of train on track #31. Note mail and express wagons on ramp (center photo) also on opposite side. Times of day these wagons are in abundance and cause a very hazardous condition, where passengers are loading or unloading. Also signals are passed to engine from ramps and when looking from engine to pointed inside of station vision is limited. Note water hydrants between track #32 and #21 Making this very close clearance between trains.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 50)
  - South End of Union Station, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 51)
    Cars in a platform with mail and express cars, men working in and about the car. Platform very often on fireman side of engine. Note roadway in foreground of photo, used constantly by tractor drivers. During moving mail "full wagon" and express to be loaded. A very dangerous crossing, fireman observing conditions while engineer taking signals or vice versa. Poor lighting in station Debris and trash, weeds cluttering up the area. This is a view of Union Station, and shows a Pennsylvania road engine at center of photo. Also at the right center of the picture notice the hand wagons that are loaded with mail and express. These wagons, the people who handle them, and the passengers who try to get on and off moving trains must be kept under observation by whichever member of the engine crew is able to see them; sometimes this is only the fireman. Notice the ground signals at the extreme left and the unkempt conditions around them. Signals are passed by hand on both sides of the engine in Union Station. Locomotive No. 5841
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 51)
  - View from 21st Street Bridge to the Northeast Towards Union Station, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 52)
    Trains moving into or out of yard. Fireman observing conditions of train as it is coming or going around curve, also prepared to take signals or emergency in case of trouble. Yard is overgrown with weeds and debris. Note overhead wires and condition of insulation, could cause trouble. TRRA Unit #501 (like P-8)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 52)
  - View from 21st Street Bridge looking Northeast, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 53)
    Showing Union Station and overhead signal bridges (Right photo); also engine moving under bridges. Note direction of engine in about station. Engines are all heading north. Again tracks curving to left best observed by fireman. Note movement of train at left side of photo, also of workman on tracks. Note condition of weeds covering tracks from left to right center of photo. Also again of water hydrants in center of photo by weed, causing close clearance between tracks. Ground signals upper center. Red and amber aspects only best observed from left side of engine. This view is to the north, atop the 21st Street viaduct. In the center of the picture note the curvature of tracks to the left. All engines operating in and around Union Station head into the station. Therefore all tracks in this picture are observed by the fireman. Signals are passed by hand on the fireman's side. There are also ground signals which the fireman observes. Note the workman in the left-center of the photograph. There are always employees working around this plant. It is essential to have a fireman to help keep these persons under observation. There is also debris in and around these tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 53)
  - View to Northeast from 21st Street Bridge, 1961 (Box 53, Folder 54)